Guide to the Papers of David Span 1936-1945 (bulk 1943) MS 580
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
David Span Papers
1938-1945 (bulk 1943)
MS 580
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.5 Linear feet (1 box)
David Span was a Jewish American who served with the Army Air Force during World War II. This collection contains approximately one hundred and thirty three letters, most of which are written by David Span to his parents, Joseph Span and Jennie Span, and to his brother, Murray Span, who was serving in the United States Army. There are also letters from Murray Span to their parents, as well as several letters to Murray from friends of his who were also serving in various branches of the Armed Forces.
Provenance
Purchase, 2007
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
David Span, a Jewish American from the Bronx, NY, was born on April 17th, 1921 to Joseph and Jennie Span. He was working as a machinist at the time of his enlistment. David Span enlisted as an Army Warrant Officer on February 18th, 1943, and was shortly after sent to Camp Upton in Long Island, New York.
David spent most of 1943 at various Army Air Force training facilities, such as the Army Air Force Technical School in Lincoln, Nebraska and Dale Mabry Field in Talahassee, Florida. David's brother, Murray, was stationed in South Carolina before being shipped to fight in France. It is not known from the letters the extent of David Span's service during the subsequent years of the war, 1944-1945. David Span died on August 20th, 1973, and was buried at the Long Island National Cemetary in Pinelawn, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains approximately one hundred and thirty three letters, most of which are written by David Span to his parents, Joseph Span and Jennie Span, and to his brother, Murray Span, who was serving in the United States Army. There are also letters from Murray Span to his parents, as well as several letters to Murray from friends of his who were also serving in various branches of the Armed Forces.
In the letters, David writes about his training in the Army Air Force at various bases across the country. There are also a few letters where he speaks about his interactions with other Jewish Americans in the Army. Highlights of the correspondence include: a 1943 letter from a Jewish chaplain to Mr. and Mrs. Span about how David would be given full opportunity to practice his religion, and a newspaper printed for airmen at Republic Aviation Corp. in Farmingdale, L.I.
In addition to the typed and hand-written letters the collection contains a telegram, a holiday card from David to Murray, and a few printed items and ephemera. One letter from Sgt. B. ["Benie"] Epstein to Mrs. H. Epstein most likely ended up with these letters due to the fact that Murray Span and "Benie" Epstein were friends, as Benie wrote him multiple letters during the War.
Arrangement
Letters are arranged chronologically by addressee. Since many letters were themselves not dated, the envelope for each letter has been placed in front of the corresponding letter.
Republic Aviation Corporation; Span, David -- 1921-1973; Span, Jennie; Span, Joseph; Span, Murray; United States. Army Air Forces. Air Base Squadron, 42nd; United States. Army Air Forces. Air Force, 18th; United States. Army Air Forces. Fighter Squadron, 312th; United States. Army Air Forces. Technical School Squadron, 905th; United States. Army Air Forces. Technical Training Command. Basic Training Center No. 10; United States. Army Air Forces; Camp Upton (N.Y.); Correspondence; Dale Mabry Field (Fl.); Envelopes; Ephemera; Greenting cards; Lincoln Air Base (Neb.); Perry Air Base (Fl.); Telegrams; World War, 1939-1945 -- Aerial operations, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- Jews -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation, Jewish
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 March (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 July (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 August (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 September (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 November (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence to Murray Span, 1943 April-December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence from Murray Span to his family, 1943 April-1945 February (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence from Jennie Span to Murray Span, 1943 December (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence to Murray Span from friends, 1943 August-1944 June (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence from Army Chaplains to Joseph and Jennie Span, 1943 July, 1943 November (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Other Correspondence to David Span, 1942 August-November, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter from Sgt. B. Epstein to Mrs. H. Epstein, 1943 November (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Printed Material and Ephemera, 1936-1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)